BETH: An individual with autism
communicates differently to their
peers often responding to verbal
communication literally and they
also use their behaviour as a way of
communicating their feelings and emotions.
It is helpful when communicating
with a person with autism spectrum
disorder to be aware of their likely
tendency towards concrete thinking.
They often don’t understand that
other people have different thoughts,
desires and needs to them and cannot
put themselves in someone else’s shoes.
They have difficulty predicting
and interpreting the behaviours of
others and may also have trouble
understanding the effects of their own
behaviour on the people around them.
JOE: Individuals with autism often
have difficulty recognising and
understanding social cues and
therefore do not instinctively
learn to adjust their behaviour
to suit different social contexts.
Their behaviour however may sometimes
exhibit itself as challenging.
This challenging behaviour is often a way
of showing their frustration anxiety or
confusion or a way of getting attention.
BETH: Behaviour exhibited by
individuals with autism can often
be deemed as inappropriate by
their peers or others around them.
This may involve them standing too
close, not showing eye contact,
interrupting conversations and not
sticking to the usual social etiquette.
If others are not aware of their
autism these behaviours can seem rude.
JOE: If an individual has sensory
problems, they may cause them to exhibit
repetitive behaviours and actions such
as hand flapping, flicking, spinning,
jumping and rocking or respond adversely
to sensory stimuli, this can bewilder
others who are unaware or unsure of these
behaviours.
BETH: It is therefore important
to know what the function of that
behaviour is and try to deal with it
as all behaviours serve a purpose.
If a trend is recognised, then
that will be the reason for the
behaviour that regularly appears,
and it can help to see what the
triggers are and how to deal with it.
JOE: It is important then to be prepared
when communicating with an individual
with autism that they have their
own individual challenges to social
interaction and having some knowledge of
the potential for behavioural issues, can
help to prevent any situations becoming
more challenging through ignorance.